According to my old memories,
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage
（ヤサコ）私の古い記憶によると
最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, 用意[ようい]:preparation/arrangements/provision, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 命[いのち]:life|lifetime|most important thing||, 命[めい]:command|life|destiny, 空っぽ[からっぽ]:empty/vacant/hollow, 器[うつわ]:bowl/vessel|ability, 器[き]:device/instrument|vessel
最初に用意された体は
命のない空っぽの器だったそうです
the body I was given
was an empty shell, without life.
ああっ…
（フミエ）ヤサコ！
Yasako!
Stay back!
Me, Satchii!
（サッチー）ボク サッチー
Yasako!
ヤサコ！
You there!
お主[おぬし]:you (when referring to one's equals or inferiors)
（メガばあ）お主ら！
ハァ ハァ… 大丈夫か？
Are you okay?
Mega-baa!
メガばあ！
（ヤサコ）
ハラケン どこに行くの？
Haraken...
Where are you going?
Haraken!
ハラケン？
ハラケン！
Haraken!
ヤサコ 大丈夫？
Yasako, are you all right?
Why is that inside my house?
なんで うちの中に？
Because I authorized it.
許可[きょか]:permission/approval|to permit
わしが許可したからじゃよ
Poop...
（京子(きょうこ)）ウンチ…
Kyoko's fever has come down a lot.
熱[ねつ]:heat|fever|zeal|, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 下がる[さがる]:to come down|to hang|to move back||
（フミエ）京子ちゃん
熱もウソみたいに下がっちゃったわ
And Densuke?
心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care
（ヤサコ）デンスケは？
（メガばあ）心配するでない
Don't you worry.
電気[でんき]:electricity|(electric) light, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
おおっ 電気も戻ったわい
Oh, the lights are back on.
Yasako, Aunty healed you...
治す[なおす]:to cure|to fix|to do over again (after -masu base of verb)||
ヤサコは
オバちゃんが治してくれたのよ
with that famous Coil-Tag.
例[れい]:custom|said|instance|, 例[ためし]:precedent/example
例のコイルタグでね
Aunty?
オバちゃんが？
I only have a few Coil-Tags.
数[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数[かず]:number/amount, 枚[まい]:counter for flat objects (e.g. sheets of paper), 枚[びら, ビラ]:bill/handbill/flier, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
コイルタグは
あと数枚でおしまいじゃ
The primary metabug for it is gone.
原料[げんりょう]:raw materials
原料のメタバグが もうなくてな
Tamako has a few that I gave her four years ago.
玉子[たまご]:eggs|hen egg|(an expert) in the making|, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, 授ける[さずける]:to grant/to award/to teach
玉子(たまこ)が持っておったのは
わしが４年前に授けたものじゃ
Where's Aunty?
ねえ オバちゃんは？
Kanna and Yasako
So, the obsolete Space is continuing to spread...
やはり:too/also|still, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 拡散[かくさん]:scattering/diffusion/spread (e.g. signal across the spectrum), 止まる[とまる]:to stop (moving)|to stop (doing, working, being supplied)|to alight, 止まる[とどまる]:to remain/to abide|to be limited to
（オバちゃん）
やはり古い空間の
拡散は止まっていない
It's the law of cause and effect.
因果[いんが]:cause and effect/karma/fate
因果なものね
Requesting access to the server.
上位[じょうい]:superior (in rank)|higher order (e.g. byte)|host computer (of connected device), コマンド:(computer) command, アクセス:access, 要求[ようきゅう]:demand/firm request/requisition
上位コマンドにアクセスを要求
In fact, this was my real task from the beginning.
やはり:too/also|still, 最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
やはり これは最初から私の仕事
Nonetheless,
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments
そして 最後のね
it's my last one.
Yes. Everyone is safe.
全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew, 無事[ぶじ]:safety/peace/quietness, 通路[つうろ]:passage/pathway/roadway, 潰す[つぶす]:to smash|to shut down|to thwart||
（オバちゃん）
ええ 全員無事よ　通路は潰した
I destroyed the passage.
I'm investigating why there was an obsolete Space in this house.
家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 調査[ちょうさ]:investigation/examination/inquiry
この家に なぜ
古い空間があったか調査中よ
Are there other injuries?
At present, there are no human casualties.
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), 被害者[ひがいしゃ]:victim/injured party/sufferer
他に被害者は？
I see...
人的[じんてき]:human/personal, 被害[ひがい]:(suffering) damage/injury/harm, 見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered
（猫目(ねこめ)）今のところ
人的被害は見つかっていない
So, there aren't any kids...
（オバちゃん）そう
もともと:originally/by nature/from the start, イマーゴ:imago, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, 子供[こども]:child/children, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
もともとイマーゴを持った
子供なんて―
who have Imago naturally.
めった:thoughtless/reckless|seldom (with neg. verb)
めったにいない
Wait.
件[くだん]:the aforementioned/the said|the usual, 件[けん]:matter/case/item, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
（猫目）
待て… 今 １件だけ見つけた
I found a single case.
A boy...
少年[しょうねん]:boy/juvenile/young boy, 歳[さい]:-years-old|ability/gift, 歳[とし]:year|age|past one's prime
少年 11歳だ
eleven years old.
An eleven year old boy...
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
まさか…
Don't tell me it's...
玉子[たまご]:eggs|hen egg|(an expert) in the making|
（猫目）玉子？
フォーマット:(computer) format, 指令[しれい]:orders/instructions/directive
（オバちゃん）
フォーマットの指令を出したわ
Tamako?
I sent the format command.
レベル:level/standard/amount
レベル３の
A level three.
（猫目）なんだと？
What?!
メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 取り上げる[とりあげる]:to pick up|to adopt|to take away|
ケンちゃんのはずがない
メガネは取り上げて…
It can't be Ken.
I confiscated his glasses.
（ヤサコ）どうしたの？
ハラケンに何か…
What's wrong?
Did something happen to Haraken?
Aunty, wait!
（ヤサコ）オバちゃん 待って！
I took away his glasses...
全員[ぜんいん]:all members (unanimity)/all hands/the whole crew, 家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, じっと:motionlessly (e.g. stand, wait)/(be) still|fixedly (e.g. gaze, stare)
全員 この家でじっとしてろ
Everyone, stay here and don't move.
Wait, Aunty!
（ヤサコ）待って オバちゃん！
What's wrong?
なんじゃ どうしたんじゃ？
あっ ヤサコ どこ行くの？
Yasako! Where are you going?
Yes. Is that so?
（オバちゃん）はい そうですか
やはり:too/also|still, メガネ:spectacles/glasses
やはり 研一(けんいち)にメガネを…
Indeed, Ken's glasses...
失礼[しつれい, しつらい]:discourtesy|Excuse me|to leave|
あっ いえ
こんな時間に失礼しました
Well, sorry for calling this late.
やはり:too/also|still, メガネ:spectacles/glasses
やはり カンナのメガネを…
As I thought,
he took Kanna's glasses.
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 法[ほう]:law|method|mood|, 条[すじ, スジ]:muscle|vein|fiber||, 条[じょう]:article (in document)|stripe|although|, 違法[いほう]:illegal/illegality/invalid, 改造[かいぞう]:remodeling/remodelling|modding, 当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||
（職員）それは電脳法12条の
違法改造に当たります
You're breaking Article 12 of the Cyberlaw.
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, 公務員[こうむいん]:government worker/public servant/civil servant, 朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||, 残業[ざんぎょう]:overtime (work)
最近の公務員は
朝まで残業するのね
I didn't know that municipal employees worked until morning these days.
内部監査[ないぶかんさ]:internal audit
（職員）
メガマスの内部監査の者です
I'm an inspector for Megamass.
ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions, 邪魔[じゃま]:hindrance|to visit (somebody's home)|demon who hinders Buddhist training
これからやることがあるの
邪魔しないでくれる？
I have things to do now.
Would you mind not bothering me?
クビになる:to be sacked/to be fired|to be beheaded
（職員）そんなことしたら
あんたクビになるぞ！
If you do that,
you'll be fired!
覚悟[かくご]:resolution/resignation/readiness
覚悟の上よ
I'm prepared for it.
辞令[じれい]:notice of personnel change (appointment, dismissal, etc.)|wording/choice of language, 受け取る[うけとる]:to receive/to get|to take
辞令は まだ受け取っていない
I haven't received a dismissal notice yet.
I'm responsible for these guys.
管理[かんり]:control/management (e.g. of a business)
この子たちは 私の管理下にある
Why are you doing all this?
あんた なぜ そこまでして？
始める[はじめる]:to start|to open (e.g. a store)|to start ...
（オバちゃん）私が始めたのよ
I'm the one who started this.
I'm the one who has to put a stop to it.
終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
私が終わらせなくてはならないわ
I'll report everything to Megamass.
件[くだん]:the aforementioned/the said|the usual, 件[けん]:matter/case/item, 全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, 報告[ほうこく]:report/information
この件は全てメガマスに報告する
Feel free.
自由[じゆう]:freedom/liberty/as it pleases you
（オバちゃん）ご自由に
Err...
（ヤサコ）あの…
（オバちゃん）んっ？
Something's happened to Haraken, hasn't it?
ハラケンに何かあったのね？
Stop.
（オバちゃん）待て
Did you run all the way here?
走る[はしる]:to run|to travel (movement of vehicles)|to hurry to||
ここまで走ってきたの？　あんた
I'm gonna come with you.
私も行くわ
理由[りゆう, わけ]:reason/pretext/motive
理由を言ってみな
Tell me your reasons.
I told him
場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach
私が場所を教えたの
where it was.
And also...
多分[たぶん]:perhaps/probably|generous
それに 私 多分 分かるの
I'm pretty sure I know
ハラケンがどこにいるか
where Haraken is.
なんだと？
What did you say?
気になる[きになる]:to be on one's mind|to feel like|to fancy, 不思議[ふしぎ]:wonder/miracle/strange, 声[こえ]:voice
前から気になってた
不思議な声がして…
I've been concerned about it.
About that strange voice.
昨日[きのう, さくじつ]:yesterday, 気づく[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise
昨日 気づいたの
Yesterday I realized
方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action)
方向だけ なんとなくだけど…
its approximate direction,
although it's just my impression...
それだけ？
Just that?
私 ハラケンのこと…
Well, I... Haraken...
危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk
危険は知っての上だな？
You know what the risks are.
Ken is using Kanna's glasses.
メガネ:spectacles/glasses
ケンちゃんは
カンナのメガネを使ってる
What on earth is happening?
位置[いち]:place/situation/position, 目指す[めざす]:to aim at/to have an eye on|to go toward
まずは その位置を目指すわ
What is "the other side,"
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||, 起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen, あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener)
（フミエ）
一体 何が起こってるの？
あっちって なんなのよ？
in reality?
I finally remembered.
思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
（メガばあ）思い出してきたわ
あれは４年前―
It was four years ago.
The incident that caused me to lose consciousness.
まさに:exactly/surely|right then, ぶっ倒れる[ぶったおれる]:to fall flat/to collapse in a heap, きっかけ:chance/start/cue, 事件[じけん]:event/affair/incident
まさに わしが ぶっ倒れる
きっかけになった事件じゃ
Four years ago?
４年前？
Four years ago,
暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, 少女[しょうじょ, おとめ]:little girl/maiden|female between 17 and 20 years old (ritsuryo period), 都市[とし]:town/city/municipal, 伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore, 調べ[しらべ]:investigation/inspection|tune
（オバちゃん）
４年前 ある暗号屋の少女が
都市伝説を調べ―
a certain girl researched urban legends,
and successfully performed a certain ritual.
儀式[ぎしき]:ceremony/rite/ritual, 導き出す[みちびきだす]:to draw (conclusion)/to deduce/to derive
１つの儀式を導き出した
A ritual?
儀式[ぎしき]:ceremony/rite/ritual
（ヤサコ）儀式？
To be precise, an encode protocol.
正確[せいかく]:accurate/punctual/exact, 暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher, 手順[てじゅん]:process/procedure/sequence
（オバちゃん）
正確に言えば 暗号の手順よ
In order to summon Miss Michiko, you see.
呼び出す[よびだす]:to summon/to call (e.g. phone)|to invoke (e.g. subroutine)
ミチコさんを呼び出すためのね
Nobody really knows exactly
起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen, 正確[せいかく]:accurate/punctual/exact
（オバちゃん）
そのとき何が起こったのかは
誰も正確には知らないわ
what happened back then.
Even that girl herself doesn't, for instance.
少女[しょうじょ, おとめ]:little girl/maiden|female between 17 and 20 years old (ritsuryo period), 本人[ほんにん]:the person himself
その少女本人もね
But the ritual was a success,
儀式[ぎしき]:ceremony/rite/ritual, 成功[せいこう]:success/hit, 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 現象[げんしょう]:phenomenon, 起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen
でも 儀式は成功し
同じような現象が起こった
and caused a phenomenon like this.
A phenomenon?
現象[げんしょう]:phenomenon
（ヤサコ）現象？
When conditions are just right, a phenomenon that
条件[じょうけん]:condition/conditions/term, そろう:careless/negligent|carelessness, そろう:to become complete/to be all present|to be equal, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 分離[ぶんり]:separation/partition/detachment, 現象[げんしょう]:phenomenon
（オバちゃん）ある条件がそろうと
電脳体が分離する現象
separates your cyberbody from your real one occurs.
The name of this phenomenon is...
現象[げんしょう]:phenomenon, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, コイル:coil
その現象の名前は電脳コイル
Dennou Coil.
Dennou Coil?
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, コイル:coil
電脳コイル？
Those Illegals do the same thing,
イリーガル:illegal, 正確[せいかく]:accurate/punctual/exact, 原因[げんいん]:cause/origin/source
（オバちゃん）
あのイリーガルもそうだけど
正確な原因は まだ分かっていない
but the nature of this phenomenon is as yet unknown.
I can't really believe Illegals do such...
イリーガル:illegal, あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
私 イリーガルが
あんなことするなんて…
The ones that appeared recently are totally different from the ones before.
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, 現れる[あらわれる]:to appear/to come in sight|to be expressed (e.g. emotions), 新顔[しんがお]:newcomer/new face, 全く[まったく]:really|indeed|good grief (expression of exasperation), 別物[べつもの]:another thing/exception/special case
（オバちゃん）ヤツらは
最近 現れた新顔とは全くの別物よ
What exactly are those Illegals?
イリーガル:illegal, 一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||
あのイリーガルは
一体なんなの？
Dangerous Illegals.
危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, イリーガル:illegal, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
危険なイリーガルじゃ
わしらはヌルと呼んでおった
We called them Null.
Null?
They are, perhaps, the oldest Illegals.
（フミエ）ヌル？
恐らく[おそらく]:perhaps/likely/probably, 一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, イリーガル:illegal
（オバちゃん）
恐らく 一番古いイリーガル
They come from the so-called C domain, an unknown Space,
ドメイン:domain, 未知[みち]:not yet known/unknown/strange, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
Ｃドメインという
未知の空間からやってきた―
and are the most primitive form of cybersubstance.
The C domain?
最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables
最初の電脳生物よ
The Coil Domain.
ドメイン:domain
（ヤサコ）Ｃドメイン？
In urban legends,
コイル:coil, ドメイン:domain
（オバちゃん）コイルドメイン
it's said to be the entrance to "the other side."
都市[とし]:town/city/municipal, 伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore, あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener), 入り口[いりぐち, いりくち]:entrance/entry/gate
都市伝説では
あっちへの入り口と言われてるわ
So, Miss Michiko is one of them?
生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal
（ヤサコ）ミチコさんって
あの生き物のことなの？
That's a possibility.
It's also the place where stray kids are taken.
しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
（オバちゃん）そうかもしれない
迷い込む[まよいこむ]:to go astray/to lose one's way, 子供[こども]:child/children, 連れる[つれる]:to lead/to take (a person), 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
迷い込んだ子供を
連れてっちゃうってとこは同じね
I didn't want anyone else to make the same mistake.
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 過ちを犯す[あやまちをおかす]:to make an error
同じ過ちを犯してほしくなかった
The same... mistake?
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 過ち[あやまち]:fault/error/indiscretion
同じ過ち？
Back then, it was my disciple who messed it all up, but...
弟子[でし, ていし]:pupil/disciple/adherent, しでかす:to make a mess/to perpetrate/to do, とはいえ:though/although/be that as it may, しんどい:tired/frazzled|tiresome, たわい:sanity/soundness of mind|drunkenness
弟子のしでかしたこととはいえ
あんときは しんどかったわい
Disciple?
弟子[でし, ていし]:pupil/disciple/adherent, 事件[じけん]:event/affair/incident, 起こす[おこす]:to raise|to wake|to cause||, 少女[しょうじょ, おとめ]:little girl/maiden|female between 17 and 20 years old (ritsuryo period)
弟子？　じゃあ
その事件を起こした少女って…
So, the girl that caused that incident was...
Right...
（オバちゃん）そう この私なのよ
（ヤサコ）えっ？
the person who called out to Michiko-san
was me.
I used to collect kirabugs.
集め[あつめ]:collecting/assembling
（オバちゃん）
私もキラバグ集めをしたわ
I used a different method than Isako.
やり方[やりかた]:manner of doing/way/method
イサコとは違うやり方だった
当時[とうじ]:at that time/in those days, 世界中[せかいじゅう]:around the world/throughout the world, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
けどね まだ当時は
世界中 古い空間だったから
Back then, all Spaces were "obsolete,"
so you could set up an encode and pick up kirabugs with your hands.
暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher, 拾い集める[ひろいあつめる]:to gather
暗号を使えば
キラバグも手で拾い集められたの
And then,
通路[つうろ]:passage/pathway/roadway, 開く[ひらく]:to open|to bloom|to open (for business, e.g. in the morning)||, 開く[あく]:to open (e.g. doors)|to open (e.g. business, etc.)|to be empty||
そして 通路を開いた
the passage opened.
何人[なんにん]:how many? (people), 何人[なにびと, なんびと]:everyone/every person/all, 子供[こども]:child/children, 意識を失う[いしきをうしなう]:to lose consciousness, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
何人か子供が意識を失ったらしいわ
I know that many kids fainted.
止める[とめる]:to stop|to park|to prevent||, 止める[やめる]:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel
もし メガばあが
止めてくれなかったら…
If Mega-baa hadn't stopped me...
Because of that, I lost all my memories from the time just before I fainted.
おかげ:grace (of God)/benevolence (of Buddha)|assistance, ぶっ倒れる[ぶったおれる]:to fall flat/to collapse in a heap, 記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage, すっかり:all/completely/totally, なくなる:to die, なくなる:to be lost (e.g. luggage)/to be missing|to be used up, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
おかげでぶっ倒れる前の記憶が
すっかりなくなってしもうたわい
（オバちゃん）
あなたたちにはすまないと思ってる
I'm very sorry for you guys.
事態[じたい]:situation/(present) state of affairs/circumstances, 避ける[さける, よける]:to avoid (physical contact with)|to avoid (situation)|to ward off, 任務[にんむ]:duty/function/office
こんな事態を避けるのが
私の任務だったのに
My mission was to prevent this situation.
フォーマット:(computer) format, 開始[かいし]:start/commencement/beginning
フォーマットの開始は あと10分よ
Ten minutes left before the format starts.
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 離れる[はなれる]:to be separated|to leave|to leave (a job, etc.)|
私から絶対に離れないようにして
Always stay with me!
It was located here ten minutes ago.
位置[いち]:place/situation/position
（オバちゃん）
10分前の位置がここよ
There's too much interference.
干渉[かんしょう]:interference/intervention/meddling, 激しい[はげしい]:violent|extreme|fervent||, 探知[たんち]:detection
干渉が激しくて
ここまでしか探知できない
I can only track it this far.
I hope that he hasn't fallen victim to the Coil phenomenon yet.
コイル:coil, 現象[げんしょう]:phenomenon, 襲う[おそう]:to attack|to succeed (someone in a post, role, etc.)|to make a sudden visit
まだコイル現象に
襲われてなければいいが
All I can do is look for him with what I have.
足[あし]:foot|leg|gait||, 足[そく]:counter for pairs (of socks, shoes, etc.), 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
あとは自分の足で探すしか…
（走る足音）
ハッ… ヤサコ？
Yasako!
Hey! Yasako, where are you?
おい ヤサコ どこだ！
Wait, Yasako!
待て ヤサコ… 何してる！
What are you doing?
It's our only chance!
お願い[おねがい]:request/wish|please
（ヤサコ）もう これしかないの
お願い 行かせて！
Please, let me go!
追いかける[おいかける]:to chase/to run after/to pursue
お前 追いかけろ！
You! Chase her!
迂回[うかい]:detour|to detour|turning movement
お前と私は迂回(うかい)だ！
You, come with me this way!
通路[つうろ]:passage/pathway/roadway, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
まだだわ
通路を見つけてからでないと…
Not yet...
If I don't find the passage...
（ヌルたち）
チョウダイ チョウダイ…
Give me...
（オバちゃん）ヤサコ どこだ？
Yasako! Where are you?!
マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|, コイル:coil, 現象[げんしょう]:phenomenon, 起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen
マズい… これでヤサコにも
コイル現象が起こったら―
Damn...
If the Coil phenomenon affects Yasako,
犠牲[ぎせい]:victim/sacrifice/scapegoat, 増える[ふえる]:to increase/to multiply, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
犠牲がまた増えてしまう
there will be another victim!
Crap!
場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 特定[とくてい]:specific/particular|specifying
クソ！　場所が特定できない
I can't identify the location!
Wait!
待て！
Ken!
ケンちゃん！
間に合う[まにあう]:to be in time for|to serve (suit, meet) the purpose/to be good enough
間に合わなかったわ
I didn't make it in time...
The passage...
通路[つうろ]:passage/pathway/roadway
通路は… 通路はどこ？
Where's the passage?!
It's not here.
（イサコ）ここにはない
Damn!
貴様[きさま]:you/you bastard|you
貴様！
Stop it! Listen to me!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., 聞ける[きける]:to tell
（イサコ）やめろ 話を聞け
If only...
お前さえ…
If only you hadn't collected kirabugs!
集める[あつめる]:to collect/to assemble/to gather
お前さえ
キラバグを集めなければ！
お前さえ… お前さえいなければ！
If only...
If only you weren't there!
Listen to me!
話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., 撃つ[うつ]:to shoot (at)|to attack/to defeat
話を聞け… 撃つな！
Don't shoot!
It's too late!
遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|, 通路[つうろ]:passage/pathway/roadway, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
もう遅い！
ケンちゃんは通路に入ってしまった
Ken has entered the passage!
What's wrong?
制御[せいぎょ]:control/governing/checking, リンク:link/directory entry
どうした？　んっ… 制御リンク
The control link?
（モジョ）モジョー
Listen to me already!
話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
話を聞け！
私も原川(はらかわ)を見つけようとしてるんだ
I'm trying to find Harakawa too!
What?
なんだと？
（警報音）
（オバちゃん）もう来たのか
Already here?
A physical format...
物理[ぶつり]:physics/law of nature, フォーマット:(computer) format
（イサコ）物理フォーマットだな？
How do you know?!
（オバちゃん）なぜ それを？
There's still a chance.
方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner
まだ方法はある
（ヌルたち）
チョウダイ チョウダイ…
Give me...
I'll separate from my cyberbody on purpose and bring him back.
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, わざと:on purpose, 分離[ぶんり]:separation/partition/detachment, 連れ戻す[つれもどす]:to bring back
（イサコ）電脳体を
わざと分離させて連れ戻すんだ
What?
（オバちゃん）何？
触る[さわる]:to touch/to feel, 分離[ぶんり]:separation/partition/detachment
（イサコ）私が行く
ヌルに触れば すぐに分離できる
I'm going there.
If the Null touches me, I'll be able to separate easily.
Even if he is deep inside, I can still bring him back.
深い[ふかい]:deep|profound|dense||, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 連れ戻す[つれもどす]:to bring back
深い所に入ってなければ
連れ戻せる
Cooperate already!
協力[きょうりょく]:cooperation/collaboration
協力しろ！
Yasako...
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
ヤサコ まさか そのつもりで…
Maybe
this was Yasako's intention?
Okonogi's here?!
（イサコ）小此木(おこのぎ)が来てるのか？
なんのつもりだ！
I believe Yasako had the same idea!
What?!
恐らく[おそらく]:perhaps/likely/probably, 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 考え[かんがえ]:thinking|idea|intention||
（オバちゃん）恐らくヤサコは
あんたと同じ考えだわ
なんだと？
Only a little time has passed since she separated.
分離[ぶんり]:separation/partition/detachment, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room
まだ分離して間もない
She should be in an area that adjoins this Space.
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 重なる[かさなる]:to be piled up|to come one after another|to overlap (each other), 重なる[おもなる]:main/principal/important, 領域[りょういき]:area/domain/territory
こっちの空間と
重なった領域にいるはずだ
来たわ
Here it is!
Can you buy me some time?
稼げる[かせげる]:to work/to earn income
時間は稼げるか？
What do you want to do?
気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
どうする気だ？
Try to delay the format as long as possible.
できるだけ:as much as one can/as much as possible/if at all possible, フォーマット:(computer) format, 遅らせる[おくらせる]:to delay/to postpone/to put off
（イサコ）できるだけ
フォーマットを遅らせてくれ
She must be around here.
辺り[あたり, ほとり]:on the bank of|(in the) neighbourhood|around (Sunday, last year, etc...)|
この辺りなんだな？
What's on your mind?
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of, まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
（猫目）
一体 何をする気なんだ まさか…
Don't tell me...!
そこだ！
There!
退避[たいひ]:taking refuge/evacuation|saving (a file)
（猫目）もう時間がない！
退避するんだ 勇子(ゆうこ)
There's no time left!
Retreat, Yuko!
It's not stable...
安定[あんてい]:stability/steadiness/equilibrium
安定しない
Okonogi! Can you hear me?
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
小此木 聞こえるか？
Okonogi!
小此木！
Amasawa...
天沢(あまさわ)さん？
ハッ… 小此木か？
Okonogi?
Amasawa?
天沢さん？　天沢さんなの？
Are you Amasawa?
With this, you can transmit an encode to another cyberbody.
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher, 移す[うつす]:to change|to change the object of one's interest or focus|to spend or take time||
これで他の電脳体にも
暗号を移せるんだな？
Wait! You can't use the last kirabug...
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments
（猫目）待て！
最後のキラバグを使うつもりか…
Okonogi! Are you there?
小此木 そこにいるな？
Amasawa! I'm here.
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
天沢さん いるわ　聞こえる
I can hear you.
There's no time!
声[こえ]:voice, 聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be, 辺り[あたり, ほとり]:on the bank of|(in the) neighbourhood|around (Sunday, last year, etc...)|, 当てる[あてる]:to hit|to expose|to apply (e.g. patch)||
（イサコ）時間がない
声が聞こえる辺りに手を当てろ
Put your hand where you hear my voice coming from.
I'm sending the encode to you.
暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher, 送る[おくる]:to send (a thing)|to take or escort (a person somewhere)|to bid farewell (to the departed)||, 当てる[あてる]:to hit|to expose|to apply (e.g. patch)||
これから暗号をそっちに送る
こいつを原川に当てるんだ
You have to put it on Harakawa.
Now, listen carefully.
聞ける[きける]:to tell, 転送[てんそう]:transfer/redirection/transmission
（イサコ）いいか？　よく聞け
これは１人しか転送できない
Only one of you can teleport with this.
足[あし]:foot|leg|gait||, 足[そく]:counter for pairs (of socks, shoes, etc.), 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
お前は自分の足で戻るんだ
You'll have to come back on foot.
Amasawa!
天沢さん 私…
I...
There's no time.
急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten
時間がない　急げ！
Hurry!
I got it!
分かったわ
Kanna...
なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
カンナ… なんて言ってるの？
What are you saying?
カンナ？
Kanna!
If I go over there, will I hear your voice, Kanna?
声[こえ]:voice, 聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
そっちに行けば
カンナの声が聞こえるの？
I'm coming to you!
許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
すぐそっちに行くから
だから許して
So please forgive me!
Kanna!
カンナ…
Haraken! Answer!
答える[こたえる]:to answer/to reply
ハラケン 答えて！
Got it! It's 2.0!
来た 2.0だ！
Damn!
物理[ぶつり]:physics/law of nature, 結界[けっかい]:(fixing) boundaries for religious practices|prohibition (of items, people, spirits, etc. that would hinder Buddhist practice)|fence between inner and outer sanctums in a temple||
チッ 物理結界か
A physical barrier!
互角[ごかく]:equality/evenness/par
じゃあ 互角だな
So, they're even.
玉子[たまご]:eggs|hen egg|(an expert) in the making|
（猫目）玉子め…
Tamako, huh...
物理[ぶつり]:physics/law of nature, 結界[けっかい]:(fixing) boundaries for religious practices|prohibition (of items, people, spirits, etc. that would hinder Buddhist practice)|fence between inner and outer sanctums in a temple||, 改造[かいぞう]:remodeling/remodelling|modding
サッチーも
物理結界に改造したのか
Did she modify Satchii and add a physical barrier?
間に合う[まにあう]:to be in time for|to serve (suit, meet) the purpose/to be good enough
間に合ってくれ
Make it in time!
ハラケン 待って！
それはカンナじゃないわ
Haraken!
Wait, that's not Kanna!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
もうやめて！
Cut it out already!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
ああ… 早く逃げるのよ
We have to run right now!
Wait.
待って
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
ダメだよ ヤサコ
まだ戻れないんだ
We can't, Yasako.
I can't go back, yet.
何言ってるの？
What are you talking about?
えっ ケン…？
"Ken..."
ケンイチ？
ハラケンのことを言ってるの？
"Ken'ichi..."
She's talking about you.
声[こえ]:voice
ヤサコ カンナの声が？
Yasako!
You can hear Kanna's voice?
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
聞こえる 聞こえるわ
I can.
I can hear it.
悲しい[かなしい]:sad/sorrowful
“悲しかった”？
"I was sad..."
ケンカ:quarrel/brawl/fight, 悲しい[かなしい]:sad/sorrowful
“研一とケンカして悲しかった”
って言ってる
She says that she was sad
about having a fight with you.
褒める[ほめる]:to praise/to admire/to speak well of someone, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me), うれしい:happy/glad/pleasant
“褒めてもらえて うれしかった”
"I was glad that you spoke well of me."
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 楽しい[たのしい]:enjoyable/fun
“一緒にいて楽しかった”
"It was fun to be with you."
“研一のことが…”
"Ken'ichi, I..."
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
“ハラケンのことが好きだった”
She...
loved you.
Me too...
僕も…
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
僕も好きだった カンナ
I loved you too!
Kanna!
さようなら:good-bye
（ヤサコ）“さようなら 研一”
"Goodbye, Ken'ichi."
責める[せめる]:to condemn|to urge|to torture|
“もう自分を責めないで”
"Stop feeling guilty about me."
（カンナ）ヤサコ
Yasako.
お願い[おねがい]:request/wish|please
研一をお願い
Take care of Ken'ichi, please.
逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
逃げて ヤサコ
Run away.
Yasako...
フォーマット:(computer) format, 音[おと, ね]:sound|note|fame|
フォーマットの音だわ
It's the sound of a format.
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
ハラケン これで戻れるわ
Haraken,
this will take you back.
がたい:body build, がたい:blastema
あり… がとう… ヤサ…
Thank you,
Yasako.
ハラケン 私…
Haraken,
I...
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
好きです
I love you!
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
私 ハラケンのことが… 好き
I love you, Haraken.
ケンちゃん？
Ken!
やったのね ヤサコ！
Yasako did it!
Right!
指令[しれい]:orders/instructions/directive, ポート:port, 捕まえる[つかまえる]:to catch/to arrest/to seize
そうだ
指令ポートだけでも捕まえれば…
If only I could use the command port...
持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
このままでは持たない
あいつを呼ぶしかない
It won't last long at this rate!
I have to call that guy...
ポチ！
Pochi!
ポート:port, ナンバー:number, 送る[おくる]:to send (a thing)|to take or escort (a person somewhere)|to bid farewell (to the departed)||
イサコ ポートナンバーを送ったわ
Isako! I sent you the port number!
Yasako! Still not here...
ヤサコ まだか？
Inside of Satchii,
we are out of reach.
内部[ないぶ]:interior/inside/internal, 対象外[たいしょうがい]:not covered (by)/not subject (to), 改造[かいぞう]:remodeling/remodelling|modding
内部は対象外なのよ
タマを改造しなくてよかったわ
I'm glad I didn't modify Tama.
んんっ…
（ヤサコ）ハラケン！
Haraken!
I verified the link.
リンク:link/directory entry, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman), 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
（オバちゃん）リンクを確認した
電脳体は間違いなく戻ってるわ
His cyberbody has definitely come back.
Oh...
そう よかった…
Thank goodness.
Nekome.
片がつく[かたがつく]:to settle (a problem)/to put an end to (a dispute)/to be disposed of
猫目 なんとか片がついたわ
I resolved this problem.
I see.
病院[びょういん]:hospital, 任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||
（猫目）
分かった 病院は任せてくれ
I'll take care of the hospital.
Yes.
残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
はい 残る手はコイルスノードしか
All that's left is the Coil Node.
But I thought it was turned off...
すでに:already/too late, 絶滅[ぜつめつ]:destruction/extinction
しかし
すでに絶滅しているのでは？
The cyberbody that was recently connected to...
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, 接続[せつぞく]:connection|changing trains|conjunction, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||
最近 接続した電脳体が？
I understand.
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
分かりました
その電脳体を捜します
I'll look for that cyberbody.
Yes.
世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 崩壊[ほうかい]:collapse/crumbling|decay, 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily
はい 世界が崩壊する前に必ず
Before the world collapses, definitely.
It's strange...
おかしい:funny/amusing|strange, 違和感[いわかん]:uncomfortable feeling/feeling out of place|malaise
おかしい…
なんだ この違和感は？
What is this uncomfortable feeling?
誰？
Who is it?!
Preview
次回[じかい]:next time (occasion), 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, コイル:coil
（ヤサコ）
次回 「電脳コイル」
Next time
on Dennou Coil:
The Black Automaton
黒い[くろい]:black|dark|illicit, オートマトン:automaton
〝黒いオートマトン 〞
The black automaton.
楽しみ[たのしみ]:enjoyment/pleasure|anticipation
お楽しみに
See you next time!